Marjorie Strider
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Marjorie Strider papers
1965-1978
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Strider, Marjorie
1.8 linear feet
The papers of pop artist, sculptor, performance artist, and art instructor Marjorie Strider date from 1965-1978, and measure 1.8 linear feet. Found within the papers are biographical materials, correspondence with colleagues and art institutions, six diaries, scattered business and financial records, notes, writings, teaching and lecture typescripts, printed material, and photographs of the "Peoples' Hole Project" of a summer class taught by Strider at the University of Iowa in 1970.
Provenance
Marjorie Strider donated her papers in 1978.
Restrictions on Access
Use or original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Marjorie Virginia Strider was born on January 26, 1931 in Guthrie, Oklahoma and attended the Kansas City Art Institute in Kansas City, Missouri, earning a Bachelor of Arts degree. After graduating, she spent two years working on window displays for the Robinson Shoe Company in Kansas City.
By the early 1960s, Strider was working as a painter-sculptor in New York City. Along with work by Andy Warhol and Roy Lichtenstein, her work was included in one of the first exhibitions of Pop Art, "First International Girlie Show" at Pace Gallery in 1965. Strider also had solo exhibitions at Pace Gallery in 1965 and 1966, and at Park College, Parkville, Missouri, in 1968.
In 1969, Strider began teaching at the School of Visual Arts in New York. During the summer of 1970, she taught at the University of Iowa in Iowa City.
In the early 1970s, Strider's work evolved into assemblage, three-dimensional multi-media organic forms, street installations, films, and performance pieces, with a characteristic theme of forms breaking out from confined spaces. One of her more famous works, Big Box, 1973, consisted of a hand-constructed cardboard carton displaying an eruption of polyurethane pouring down the side. In 1973 and 1974, Strider had solo exhibitions at the Nancy Hoffman Gallery in New York City.
Strider also participated in group exhibitions at the Felix Handschin Gallery in Basel, Switzerland in 1970, at Boston Museum in 1972, at New York's School of Visual Arts in 1973 and, in 1974, at the Virginia Museum of Art and Storm King Art Center.
Strider's works are in the collections of the Albright-Knox Museum, Des Moines Art Center, New York University, Wadsworth Atheneum, and the Hirshhorn Museum and Sculpture Garden.
Marjorie Strider lives in New York City.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of pop artist, sculptor, performance artist, and art instructor Marjorie Strider date from 1965-1978, and measure 1.8 linear feet. Found within the papers are biographical materials, correspondence with colleagues and art institutions, six diaries, scattered business and financial records, notes, writings, teaching and lecture typescripts, printed material, and photographs of the "Peoples' Hole Project" of a summer class taught by Strider at the University of Iowa in 1970.
Biographical materials include an address book. Correspondence is primarily between Strider, colleagues, and art institutions concerning exibitions and art-related activities. Six diaries dated from 1968 through 1973 contain very brief daily entries. Business records are primarily financial, but also include contracts for a commissioned poster for the HKL, Ltd. Project "Ikebana International," and for a merger between the stockholders of Chick Pea Conspiracy, Inc. and Max's Kansas City, Inc.
A teaching file contains material relating to a 1970 summer class taught by Strider and Scott Burton at the University of Iowa contains the best documentation about Strider's ideas about art. Included here are notes outlining various assignments for street performances and avant-garde uses of public spaces, writings by students describing their assignments, miscellaneous printed material, and notes, writings, clippings, and photographs concerning the "Peoples' Hole Project."
Additional notes and writings include miscellaneous teaching and lecture typescripts, a list of artists' names, and miscellaneous notes. Printed material includes clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, prospectuses, and press releases.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into 7 series arranged chronologically:
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1968 (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1966-1977 (Box 1: 25 folders)
Series 3: Diaries, 1968-1973 (Box 1; 3 folders)
Series 4: Business Records, 1965-1976 (Boxes 1-2; 56 folders)
Series 5: Teaching File from University of Iowa, Iowa City, 1970 (Box 3; 11 folders)
Series 6: Notes and Writings, 1970-1977 (Box 3; 9 folders)
Series 7: Printed Material, 1966-1978 (Box 3; 6 folders)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed under the following terms:
Subjects:
University of Iowa -- Faculty
Subjects-Topical:
Art -- Philosophy; Art -- Study and teaching; Art teachers -- United States; Performance artists -- New York (State)$zNew York; Pop art -- New York (State) -- New York; Women sculptors -- New York (State) -- New York
Types of Materials:
Diaries; Photographs; Writings
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, circa 1968, Series 1:; (Box 1; 1 folder)
  Biographical material consists of a Social Security application card that does not display Strider's Social Security number, and an address book.
  - Social Security Application Card and Address Book, 1968, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1966-1977, Series 2:; (Box 1: 25 folders)
  Correspondence is primarily between Strider, colleagues, and art institutions concerning exhibitions and art-related activities. There is one card from actor Donald Buka and an illustrated calling card from writer John Patrick Sullivan.
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1970, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Correspondence, 1971, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Correspondence, 1972, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - Correspondence, 1973, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 12-14)
  - Correspondence, 1974, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 15-17)
  - Correspondence, 1975, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 18-21)
  - Correspondence, 1976, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 22-25)
  - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Diaries, 1968-1973, Series 3:; (Box 1; 3 folders)
  Six diaries contain very brief entries concerning Strider's daily activities.
  - Diaries, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Diaries, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Diaries, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Business Records, 1965-1976, Series 4:; (Boxes 1-2; 56 folders)
  Business records primarily consist of financial records, such as banking records, receipts, a ledger, and records of wages. Also included are contracts for a commissioned poster for the HKL, Ltd. Project "Ikebana International," and for a merger between the stockholders of Chick Pea Conspiracy, Inc. and Max's Kansas City, Inc.
  - Contracts, 1968-1972 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Records of Wages, 1968-1976, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Tax Records, 1970-1975 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Ledger of Expenditures, 1965-1971 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Notebook of Expenditures, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Check Stubs, 1966-1969, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Check Stubs, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Check Stubs, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Check Stubs, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Check Stubs, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Check Stubs, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Check Stubs, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Cancelled Checks, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Cancelled Checks, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Cancelled Checks, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Cancelled Checks, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Cancelled Checks, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Cancelled Checks, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts, 1967-1969, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts, 1970, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 49-52)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts, 1971, (9 folders) (Box 1, Folder 53-61)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts, 1971, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts, 1972, (5 folders) (Box 2 (hol), Folder 3-7)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts, 1973, (6 folders) (Box 2 (hol), Folder 8-13)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts, 1974, (4 folders) (Box 2 (hol), Folder 14-17)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts, 1975, (4 folders) (Box 2 (hol), Folder 18-21)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts, 1976, (3 folders) (Box 2 (hol), Folder 22-24)
- Teaching File from University of Iowa, Iowa City, 1970, Series 5:; (Box 3; 11 folders)
  These files contain material relating to a 1970 summer class taught by Strider and Scott Burton at the University of Iowa in Iowa City. Included are notes describing various assignments and writings by students, miscellaneous printed material, and notes, writings, clippings, and photographs concerning the "Peoples' Hole Project."
  - Miscellaneous Notes and Writings by Students, 1970, (6 folders) (Box 3, Folder 1-6)
  - Writings and Printed Material Concerning Student Roberta Krasner, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - "People's Hole Project" Notes, Writings, and Clippings, 1970, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
  - "People's Hole Project" Photographs, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Notes and Writings, 1970-1977, Series 6:; (Box 3; 9 folders)
  This series contains teaching and lecture typescripts, a list of artists' names, and miscellaneous notes.
  - Miscellaneous Teaching Notes, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous Teaching Notes, 1973-1975 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Lecture Notes, 1973-1974, (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 14-17)
  - Lists of Artists' Names, 1974-1977 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Notebook Containing Miscellaneous Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, 1971-1973, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Printed Material, 1966-1978, Series 7:; (Box 3; 6 folders)
  Printed material consists of clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, prospectuses, press releases, and miscellaneous printed material.
  - Clippings, 1967-1975, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1972-1978 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Prospectuses, 1975, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Press Releases, 1966-1972, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1973-1976, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 25-26)